Guide to the David Weiner Papers on the United Federation of Teachers TAM.164
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Weiner Papers on the United Federation of Teachers
1924-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weiner, David
TAM.164
8.25 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes and one half manuscript box
From the 1960s to the 1990s, educator and activist David Weiner was a member of the Teachers Union of New York and the United Federation of Teachers. He was also a member of the left-wing opposition group the Teachers Action Caucus. This collection consists of materials from his involvement in those organizations. Included are correspondence, notes, agendas and minutes, article drafts and publications, newsletters, clippings, broadsides, and promotional materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by David Weiner in 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 2003.028.
Historical/Biographical Note
David Weiner was an educator and activist. He was a member of the Teachers Union of New York, and subsequently, the United Federation of Teachers, where he was a member of the left-wing opposition group the Teachers Action Caucus. Weiner also was active in the retired teachers chapter of the UFT, and at one time edited its newsletter.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
For more information about the United Federation of Teachers, see the following collections:
United Federation of Teachers Records, WAG.022
Teachers Action Caucus (United Federation of Teachers), TAM.141
United Action Caucus (American Federation of Teachers), TAM.338
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains material related to the United Federation of Teachers (UFT) and the UFT's Teachers Action Caucus and Retired Teachers Committee. The collection also holds materials on 20th-century education issues, such as academic freedom, school desegregation, civil rights, the Cold War, and the Vietnam War. Document types include correspondence, notes, agendas and minutes, article drafts and publications, newsletters, clippings, broadsides, and promotional materials.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 2 series: Series I, David Weiner's United Federation of Teachers records; and Series II, Subject files.
Jewish communists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Academic freedom.; School integration; Cold War.; Teachers' Union of the City of New York; United Federation of Teachers. Retired Teachers Chapter; Teachers Action Caucus
- Series I: David Weiner's United Federation of Teachers records, 1949-2006; 4 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains United Federation of Teachers materials, such as minutes, correspondence, conference proceedings, and reports, collected by David Weiner.
  - Teachers Union, Rosenbaum Case, Correspondence, Informer Notes, Minutes, notes, 1949-1959 (Box 1)
  - Teacher Salary Trends, Teachers Union Constitution, History of Teachers Union, Dissolution, Teachers Strike, Teachers for Community Control, 1955-1969 (Box 2)
  - Names, Lists, Budget, Decentralization, Election Materials, Reinstatement, Black Caucus, 1968-1990 (Box 3)
  - Positions, AFT Crisis Report, Teachers Action Newsletter, Constitution, Retired Teachers Chapter, 1973-1991 (Box 4)
  - Other caucuses, AFT and CIA, New Action Coalition, Retired Teachers Chapter update, 1979-1991 (Box 5)
  - Membership Minutes, Retired Teachers Chapter/UFT Minutes, Surveys of Retired Teachers, Teachers Retirement Board meetings, 1987-2006 (Box 6)
  - Democracy in the United Federation of Teachers, UFT Election, Welfare Fund, Retired Teachers Committee/UFT minutes, 1990-2002 (Box 7)
  - Retiree Advocate, Retiree Advocate Questionnaire, Correspondence, Pensions, Borough Meetings, 1995-2006 (Box 8)
  - Teachers Action Caucus, 1966-1992 (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1924-2004
  Series II contains articles, notes, clippings, and reports collected and arranged by subject by David Weiner.
  - Academic Freedom - Civil Defense in Schools, 1949-1977 (Box 14)
  - Cold War and the Schools - Labor, 1924-2002 (Box 15)
  - Loyalty Oaths - Racism, 1949-1995 (Box 16)
  - Racism - Vietnam, 1939-2004 (Box 17)